Dr. Bora Uyar https://borauyar@mdc-berlin.de

Bioinformatics Scientist

Hannoversche Str. 28 Berlin 10115 Germany \Box +49 123 456789 n borauyar in bora-uyar-11050425 arcas.ai



Summary

I am a Bioinformatics Scientist at the Bioinformatics & Omics Data Science platform of the Max-Delbrück-Center for Molecular Medicine. My roles in the platform include research, collaborations with other labs in the institute, and supporting other researchers in the form of consultations, mentorships, workshops, and user-friendly software development for wet-lab researchers. I am also a member of the arcas.ai team, where my current research is focused on development of deep learning-based multi-modal data integration tools for precision oncology. My work in the last 15 years spanned various categories such as comparative genomics, protein sequence analysis in the context of molecular interactions and disease mechanisms, RNA bioinformatics, and omics data science with a focus on development of reproducible software for the bioinformatics community.

Experience

2015-Present Bioinformatics Scientist, Max-Delbrück-Center for Molecular Medicine, Berlin, Germany

- O Conduct research and collaborations with other labs.
- O Support researchers through consultations, mentorships, and workshops.
- Develop user-friendly software for wet-lab researchers.

2014–2015 Postdoctoral Fellow, European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany

Education

2011–2014 Ph.D. in Bioinformatics, European Molecular Biology Laboratory, Heidelberg, Germany

2008-2010 M.Sc. in Bioinformatics, Simon Fraser University, BC Cancer Agency, Vancouver,

2003–2008 B.Sc. in Biological Sciences, Sabanci University, Istanbul, Turkey

Skills

Languages

Programming Python, R, Bash/Shell (Active); Perl, C++, SQL (Familiar/Past)

Deep PyTorch, PyTorch Lightning, PyTorch Geometric (*Active*); TensorFlow, Keras (*Fa*-Learning *miliar/Past*)

Development

Machine Random Forests, SVMs, GLMnet

Learning

Methods

Version Git (Active); Subversion (Familiar/Past)

Control

Workflows Snakemake (Active); CWL (Familiar/Past)

Package Conda, Guix (Active); Docker (Familiar/Past)

Management

Data Science CRAN/Bioconductor, Python libraries (scikit-learn, NumPy, pandas, Matplotlib)

Toolkits

Keywords Omic data science for precision oncology, protein language models, causal network

analysis, single-cell data analysis (Active); Comparative genomics, short linear motifs

(Familiar/Past)

Profiles

Google scholar.google.com/YEZr1LUAAAAJ

Scholar

GitHub github.com/borauyar

ORCID orcid.org/0000-0002-3170-4890

LinkedIn linkedin.com/in/bora-uyar-11050425

News Articles

- New textbook for computational genomics (mdc-berlin.de)
- Searching the sewers for viruses (bionity.com)
- Al identifies cancer cells (bionity.com)
- Parallel Genome Editing in Microscopic Worms Maps Regulatory Genomic Elements to Physiology (genengnews.com)
- Stray proteins cause genetic disorders (sciencedaily.com)
- A genetic chaperone for healthy aging? (bionity.com)

Selected Publications

Genome Identifying tumor cells at the single-cell level using machine learning

Biology, 2022

Cell Reports, Parallel genetics of regulatory sequences using scalable genome editing in vivo

2021

Aging Single-cell analyses of aging, inflammation and senescence

Research

Reviews, 2020

GigaScience, PiGx: reproducible genomics analysis pipelines with GNU Guix 2018

Cell, 2018 Mutations in Disordered Regions Can Cause Disease by Creating Dileucine Motifs

Nucleic Acids RCAS: an RNA centric annotation system for transcriptome-wide regions of interest Research, 2017